<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Boost//DTD BoostBook XML V1.0//EN"
  "http://www.boost.org/tools/boostbook/dtd/boostbook.dtd">

  <chapter id="bbv2.advanced">
    <title>Advanced</title>

  <para>This section will document
  mostly high-level view of Boost.Build, mentioning appropriate
  modules and rules. The on-line help system must be used to obtain
  low-level documentation (see the <link linkend=
  "bbv2.reference.init.options.help">help option</link>).</para>

    <section id="bbv2.advanced.overview">
      <title>Overview</title>

  <para>The most fundemental entity in Boost.Build is <emphasis>main
  target</emphasis>. This is object that user want to construct from
  sources and keep up to date with regard to those sources. Typical
  examples of main targets are executable files and libraries.</para>

  <para>Main targets are grouped in <emphasis>projects</emphasis>. Their main
  purpose is organization: related targets placed in one project,
  can then be built together, or share some definitions.</para>

  <para>Main targets and projects are created as the result of reading
  one or several Jamfiles. Each Jamfile is a file written in
  Boost.Jam interpreted language, and typically contains calls to
  functions provided by Boost.Build, which create main targets of
  needed type, declare project attributes and access other
  projects. The full list of functions provided by Boost.Build is
  described <link linkend="bbv2.advanced.builtins">below</link>.
  Of course, user can create his own functions, or it can directly
  access Boost.Build internals from Jamfile, if builtin facilities are
  not sufficient.</para>

  <para>Each main target, or project can be built in a number of ways,
  say with optimization or without. We'll call such entities
  "metatargets". To make Boost.Build produce any real targets, user
  issues <link linkend="bbv2.reference.buildreq">build request</link>,
  which specifies metatargets to be built, and properties to be
  used.</para>

  <para>The <emphasis>properties</emphasis> are just (name,value) pairs that
  describe various aspects of constructed objects, for example:</para>
  <programlisting>
&lt;optimization&gt;full &lt;inlining&gt;off
</programlisting>

  <para>Given the built request, Boost.Build figures out the targets
  needed for requested metatargets with requested properties, how
  they can be created, and whether exising files can be reused. It
  finally issues command to create needed files, automatically
  converting properties into appropricate command line options.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.advanced.roadmap">
      <title>Your first project and roadmap</title>

  <para>Creating your first project requires three steps:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem><simpara>Create an empty file called "Jamfile"</simpara></listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Create an empty file called "project-root.jam"
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Either set your <envar>BOOST_BUILD_PATH</envar> environment
    variant to Boost.Build root, or create a "boost-build.jam" file
    with the following content:

<programlisting>
boost-build /path/to/boost.build ;
</programlisting>

      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>After that, you can run the "bjam" command in the directory
  where you've created the files. Surely, it won't do anything, but
  it will run without error, at least. Your next steps might
  be:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Adding new main targets to the "Jamfile" file. The basic
    syntax for declaring a main target is described <link linkend=
    "bbv2.advanced.targets">below</link>, and all builtin functions for
    declaring main targets are <link linkend=
    "bbv2.advanced.builtins.targets">listed</link>.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Creating subprojects. Create a directory, put new Jamfile
    there, and move some main targets to that Jamfile, or declare
    new ones. The <link linkend="bbv2.advanced.projects">projects
    reference</link> will help with this part.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Customizing Boost.Build for your needs. You might have
    additional tools you want to run, or just want different
    extension for some file. The <ulink url=
    "doc/extending.html">extender manual</ulink> is waiting for
    you.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.advanced.targets">
      <title>Main targets</title>

      <para id="bbv2.advanced.targets.main">
        <emphasis>Main target</emphasis> is a user-defined named
  entity which can be build, for example a named executable file.
  Declaring a main target is usually done using one of <link linkend=
        "bbv2.advanced.builtins.targets">main target functions</link>.
        The user can also declare <ulink url=
  "doc/extending.html#main_target_rules">custom main target
  function</ulink>.</para>

  <para>Most main targets rules in Boost.Build use similiar
  syntax:</para>

<programlisting>
function-name main-target-name 
    : sources 
    : requirements 
    : default-build 
    : usage-requirements 
    ;
</programlisting>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        "main-target-name" is the name used to request the target
    on command line and to use it from other main targets. Main
    target name may contain alphanumeric characters and symbols '-'
    and '_';
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        "sources" is the list of source files and other main
    targets that must be combined. If source file is specified
    using relative path, it's considered to be relative to the
    source directory of the project where the path is used. See the
    <link linkend=
    "bbv2.advanced.projects.attributes.projectrule">project</link> rule
    for information how to change source directory.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        "requirements" is the list of properties that must always
    be present when this main target is built.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        "default-build" is the list of properties that will be used
    unless some other value of the same feature is already
    specified.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        "usage-requirements" is the list of properties that will be
    propagated to all main targets that use this one, i.e. to all
    dependedents.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Some main target rules have shorter list of parameters, and
  you should consult their documentation for details.</para>

  <para>Building of the same main target can differ greatly from
  platform to platform. For example, you might have different list
  of sources for different compilers. Therefore it is possible to
  invoke main target rules several times for a single main target.
  For example:</para>

<programlisting>
exe a : a_gcc.cpp : &lt;toolset&gt;gcc ;
exe a : a.cpp ;
</programlisting>

      <para>
      Each call to the 'exe' rule defines a new <emphasis>main target
      alternative</emphasis> for the main target <literal>a</literal>.
      In this case, the first alternative will be used for the
      <command>gcc</command> toolset, while the second alternative will
      be used in other cases. See <link linkend=
      "bbv2.reference.buildprocess.alternatives">below</link> for
      details.
      </para>

  <para>Sometime a main target is really needed only by some other
  main target. E.g. a rule that declared test-suite uses a main
  target that represent test, but those main targets are rarely
  needed by themself.</para>

  <para>It possible to declare target inline, i.e. the "sources"
  parameter may include call to other main rules. For example:</para>

<programlisting>
exe hello : hello.cpp 
    [ obj helpers : helpers.cpp : &lt;optimization&gt;off ] ;
</programlisting>

      <para>
Will cause "helpers.cpp" to be always compiled without
optimization. It's possible to request main targets declared
inline, but since they are considered local, they are renamed to
"parent-main-target_name..main-target-name". In the example above,
to build only helpers, one should run "bjam hello..helpers".
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.advanced.projects">
      <title>Projects</title>

  <para>Boost.Build considers every software it build as organized
  into <emphasis>projects</emphasis> &#x2014; modules which declare targets.
  Projects are organized in a hierarchical structure, so each
  project may have a single parent project and a number of
  subprojects.</para>

  <para>Most often, projects are created as result of loading
  <emphasis>Jamfile</emphasis> &#x2014; files which are specially meant to
  describe projects. Boost.Build will implicitly load Jamfile in
  the invocation directory, and all Jamfiles referred by the first
  one, creating the hierarchy of projects.</para>

  <para>The exact name of file that describes project is configurable.
  By default, it's <literal>Jamfile</literal>, but can be changed by setting
  global variables <literal>JAMFILE</literal>, for example in
  <literal>boost-build.jam</literal> file. The value of the variable is a
  list of regex patterns that are used when searching for Jamfile
  in a directory.</para>

  <para>Every Boost.Build modules can decide to act as project and be
  able to declare targets. For example, the
  <filename>site-config.jam</filename> module can declare libraries
  available on a given host, as described <ulink url=
  "doc/recipes.html#site_config_targets">here</ulink>.</para>

  <para>There are three things that can be put in Jamfile:
  declarations of main targets, calls to a number of predefined
  rules, and arbitrary user code. The predefined rules are listed
  below:</para>

  <table>
    <title/>
    <tgroup cols="2">
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Rule</entry>

          <entry>Semantic</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>

      <tbody>
    <row>
      <entry><link linkend=
      "bbv2.advanced.projects.attributes.projectrule">project</link>
      </entry>

      <entry>Define project attributes.</entry>
    </row>

    <row>
      <entry><link linkend=
      "bbv2.advanced.projects.relationships.useprojectrule">use-project</link></entry>

      <entry>Make another project known.</entry>
    </row>

    <row>
      <entry><link linkend=
      "bbv2.advanced.projects.relationships.buildprojectrule">build-project</link></entry>

      <entry>Build another project when this one is built.</entry>
    </row>

    <row>
      <entry><link linkend=
      "bbv2.reference.buildprocess.explict">explicit</link></entry>

      <entry>States that the target should be built only by explicit
      request.</entry>
    </row>

    <row>
      <entry>glob</entry>

      <entry>Takes a list of wildcards, and returns the list of files
      which match any of the wildcards.</entry>
    </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

  <para>Each project is also associated with <emphasis>project root</emphasis>.
  That's a root for a tree of projects, which specifies some global
  properties.</para>

      <section id="bbv2.advanced.projects.root">
        <title>Project root</title>

        <para>
          Project root for a projects is the nearest parent directory
          which contains a file called
          <filename>project-root.jam</filename>. That file defines
          certain properties which apply to all projects under project
          root. It can:

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        configure toolsets, via call to <literal>toolset.using</literal>
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        refer to other projects, via the <literal>use-project</literal>
        rule
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        declare constants, via the <literal>constant</literal> and
        <literal>path-constant</literal> rules.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

      </para>

  <para>To facilitate declaration of simple projects, Jamfile and
  project-root can be merged together. To achieve this effect, the
  project root file should call the <literal>project</literal> rule. The
  semantic is precisely the same as if the call was made in
  Jamfile, except that project-root.jam will start serve as
  Jamfile. The Jamfile in the directory of project-root.jam will be
  ignored, and project-root.jam will be able to declare main
  targets as usual.</para>

      </section>

      <section id="bbv2.advanced.projects.attributes">
        <title>Project attributes</title>

  <para>For each project, there are several attributes.</para>

  <para><emphasis>Project id</emphasis> is a short way to denote a project, as
  opposed to the Jamfile's pathname. It is a hierarchical path,
  unrelated to filesystem, such as "boost/thread". <link linkend=
  "bbv2.advanced.ids">Target references</link> make use of project ids to
  specify a target.</para>

  <para><emphasis>Source location</emphasis> specifies the directory where sources
  for the project are located.</para>

  <para><emphasis>Project requirements</emphasis> are requirements that apply to
  all the targets in the projects as well as all subprojects.</para>

  <para><emphasis>Default build</emphasis> is the build request that should be
  used when no build request is specified explicitly.</para>

  <para id="bbv2.advanced.projects.attributes.projectrule">
  The default values for those attributes are
  given in the table below. In order to affect them, Jamfile may
  call the <literal>project</literal> rule. The rule has this
  syntax:</para>

<programlisting>
project id : &lt;attributes&gt; ;
</programlisting>

        <para>
Here, attributes is a sequence of (attribute-name,
attribute-value) pairs. The list of attribute names along with its
handling is also shown in the table below. For example, it it
possible to write:
        </para>

<programlisting>
project tennis 
    : requirements &lt;threading&gt;multi 
    : default-build release
    ;
</programlisting>

  <table>
    <title/>
    <tgroup cols="4">
      <thead>
    <row>
      <entry>Attribute</entry>

      <entry>Name for the 'project' rule</entry>

      <entry>Default value</entry>

      <entry>Handling by the 'project' rule</entry>
    </row>
      </thead>

      <tbody>

    <row>
      <entry>Project id</entry>

      <entry>none</entry>

      <entry>none</entry>

      <entry>Assigned from the first parameter of the 'project' rule.
      It is assumed to denote absolute project id.</entry>
    </row>

    <row>
      <entry>Source location</entry>

      <entry><literal>source-location</literal></entry>

      <entry>The location of jamfile for the project</entry>

      <entry>Sets to the passed value</entry>
    </row>

    <row>
      <entry>Requirements</entry>

      <entry><literal>requirements</literal></entry>

      <entry>The parent's requirements</entry>

      <entry>The parent's requirements are refined with the passed
      requirement and the result is used as the project
      requirements.</entry>
    </row>

    <row>
      <entry>Default build</entry>

      <entry><literal>default-build</literal></entry>

      <entry>none</entry>

      <entry>Sets to the passed value</entry>
    </row>

    <row>
      <entry>Build directory</entry>

      <entry><literal>build-dir</literal></entry>

      <entry>If parent has a build dir set, the value of it, joined
      with the relative path from parent to the current project.
      Otherwise, empty</entry>

      <entry>Sets to the passed value, interpreted as relative to the
      project's location.</entry>
    </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>
      </section>

      <section id="bbv2.advanced.projects.relationships">
        <title>Project relationship</title>

  <para>There are three kinds of project relationships.</para>

  <para>First is parent-child. This relationship is established
  implicitly: parent directories of a project are searched, and the
  first found Jamfile is assumed to define the parent project. The
  parent-child relationship affects only attribute values for the
  child project.</para>

  <para id="bbv2.advanced.projects.relationships.buildprojectrule">
  Second is build relationship. Some
  project may request to recursively build other projects. Those
  project need not be child projects. The <literal>build-project</literal>
  rule is used for that:</para>
  <programlisting>
    build-project src ;   
</programlisting>

  <para id="bbv2.advanced.projects.relationships.useprojectrule">
  The third kind is the 'use'
  relationship. In means that one project uses targets from
  another. It is possible to just refer to target in other projects
  using target id. However, if target id uses project id, it is
  required that the project id is known. The
  <literal>use-project</literal>
  rule is employed to guarantee that.
  </para>

<programlisting>
use-project ( id : location )
</programlisting>

        <para>
It loads the project at the specified location, which makes
its project id available in the project which invokes the rule. It
is required that the <literal>id</literal> parameter passed to the
<literal>use-project</literal> rule be equal to the id that the loaded
project declared. At this moment, the <literal>id</literal> paremeter
should be absolute project id.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
   
    <section id="bbv2.advanced.ids">
      <title>Target identifiers and references</title>

      <para><emphasis>Target identifier</emphasis> is used to denote a
      target. The syntax is:</para>

<programlisting>
target-id -&gt; (project-id | target-name | file-name )
              | (project-id | directory-name) "//" target-name   
project-id -&gt; path
target-name -&gt; path
file-name -&gt; path
directory-name -&gt; path                  
</programlisting>

      <para>
This grammar allows some elements to be recognized as either

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        project id (at this point, all project ids start with slash).
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        name of target declared in current Jamfile (note that target
        names may include slash).
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        a regular file, denoted by absolute name or name relative to
        project's sources location.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  To determine the real meaning a check is made if project-id
  by the specified name exists, and then if main target of that
  name exists. For example, valid target ids might be:

<screen>
a                                    -- target in current project
lib/b.cpp                            -- regular file
/boost/thread                        -- project "/boost/thread"
/home/ghost/build/lr_library//parser -- target in specific project
</screen>

    </para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Rationale:</emphasis>Target is separated from project by special
  separator (not just slash), because:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        It emphasises that projects and targets are different things.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        It allows to have main target names with slashes. 

    <!-- The motivation for which is:

    So, to summarize:

    1. The project which extract tarfile may extract all possible kinds
       of targets, and it's reasonable to use them directly from other
       project.

    2. The rule for unpacking tar is inplemented in terms of
       "patch-file", for maintainability, and therefore, must use main
       target name which contains slashes?

    3. Using sub-Jamfile in "foo" to declare extracted file "foo/b" is
       not an option, because you should not change existing tree 

    That makes good rationale for why main target must contain names.
    -->
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para id="bbv2.advanced.targets.references">
    <emphasis>Target reference</emphasis> is used to
  specify a source target, and may additionally specify desired
  properties for that target. It has this syntax:</para>

<programlisting>
target-reference -&gt; target-id [ "/" requested-properties ]
requested-properties -&gt; property-path
</programlisting>

      <para>
For example,

<programlisting>
exe compiler : compiler.cpp libs/cmdline/&lt;optimization&gt;space ;
</programlisting>

would cause the version of <literal>cmdline</literal> library,
optimized for space, to be linked in even if the
<literal>compiler</literal> executable is build with optimization for
speed.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="bbv2.advanced.builtins">
      <title>Builtin facilities</title>

      <section id="bbv2.advanced.builtins.targets">
        <title>Main targets</title>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term><literal>exe</literal></term>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Creates a regular executable file. Sources must be either
        object files or libraries, and sources of different types
        will be converted to accepted types automatically.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><literal>lib</literal></term>

    <listitem>
      <para>Creates a library file. Depending on the value of
      &lt;link&gt; feature the library will be either static or
      shared. Like with "exe", sources will be converted either to
      objects or libraries.</para>

      <para>The handling of libraries in sources depends on whether
      linking is static or shared. For shared linking, libraries
      will be linked in. For static linking the library sources
      will not be linked in, since it's not possible, and will be
      passed on. Other main target which depend on this one will
      see those libraries and link to it. Therefore, putting
      library in sources of other library works in all cases.</para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><literal>alias</literal></term>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Builds all the source targets and returns them unmodified.
        Please run "bjam --help alias" for more details.
      </simpara>
    </listitem></varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><literal>stage</literal></term>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Copies a number of targets to a single directory. The
    primary purpose is installing binaries. Please run "bjam --help
    stage" for more details.
      </simpara>
    </listitem></varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><literal>unit-test</literal> (from module "testing")</term>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Creates an executable file and runs it. Build won't succeed
    unless the executable runs successfully. The rule is usefull
    for creating test program which should be rerun whenever any
    dependency changes. <!-- make? -->
      </simpara>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

      </section>

      <section id="bbv2.advanced.builtins.features">
        <title>Features</title> 

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry><term><literal>variant</literal></term>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
      The feature which combines several low-level features in
      order to make building most common variants simple.
      </simpara>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Allowed values:</emphasis> <literal>debug</literal>, <literal>release</literal>,
      <literal>profile</literal></para>

      <para>The value <literal>debug</literal> expands to</para>

<programlisting>
&lt;optimization&gt;off &lt;debug-symbols&gt;on &lt;inlining&gt;off &lt;runtime-debugging&gt;on
</programlisting>

      <para>The value <literal>release</literal> expands to</para>

<programlisting>
&lt;optimization&gt;speed &lt;debug-symbols&gt;off &lt;inlining&gt;full &lt;runtime-debugging&gt;off
</programlisting>

      <para>The value <literal>profile</literal> expands to the same as
      <literal>release</literal>, plus:</para>

<programlisting>
&lt;profiling&gt;on &lt;debug-symbols&gt;on
</programlisting>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Rationale:</emphasis> Runtime debugging is on in debug build
      so suit expectations of people used various IDEs. It's
      assumed other folks don't have any specific expectation in
      this point.</para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><literal>link</literal></term>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Feature which controls how libraries are built.
      </simpara>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Allowed values:</emphasis> <literal>shared</literal>,
      <literal>static</literal></para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><literal>library</literal></term>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        For exe and lib main targets, the &lt;library&gt;X feature
    is equvivalent to putting X in the list of sources. The feature
    is sometimes more convenient: you can put &lt;library&gt;X in
    the requirements for a project and it will be linked to all
    executables.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><literal>use</literal></term>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Causes the target referenced by the value of this feature
    to be constructed and adds it's usage requirements to build
    properties. The constructed targets are not used in any other
    way. The primary use case is when you use some library and want
    it's usage requirements (such as include paths) to be applied,
    but don't want to link to the library.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><literal>dll-path</literal></term>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Specify a path where dynamic libraries should be found at
    where executable or shared library is run. This feature
    directly affects binaries with the gcc compiler, allowing them
    to pick specific libraries, and ignoring all environment
    settings. On other toolsets, the binary still requires proper
    environment settings to be run. However, Boost.Build tools
    which run executables will notice dll-path settings and create
    this environment automatically.
      </simpara>
    </listitem></varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term><literal>hardcode-dll-paths</literal></term>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
      Controls automatic generation of dll-path properties.
      </simpara>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Allowed values:</emphasis> <literal>off</literal>, <literal>on</literal> When this
      property is on, usage requirements for each library will
      include additional dll-path propertry, with the path the the
      generated library file. This allows to run executables
      without placing all the dependent libraries to a single
      location.</para>
    </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

