<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Boost//DTD BoostBook XML V1.0//EN"
  "http://www.boost.org/tools/boostbook/dtd/boostbook.dtd">

  <chapter id="bbv2.reference">
    <title>Detailed reference</title>

    <section id="bbv2.reference.features">
      <title>Features and properties</title>

      <section id="bbv2.reference.features.defined">
        <title>Definitions</title>

  <para>A <emphasis>feature</emphasis> is a normalized (toolset-independent)
  aspect of a build configuration, such as whether inlining is
  enabled. Feature names may not contain the '<literal>&gt;</literal>'
  character.</para>

  <!--
    And what about dash?
  -->

  <para>Each feature in a build configuration has one or more
  associated <emphasis>value</emphasis>s. Feature values for non-free features
  may not contain the '<literal>&lt;</literal>', '<literal>:</literal>', or
  '<literal>=</literal>' characters. Feature values for free features may not
  contain the '<literal>&lt;</literal>' character.</para>

  <para>A <emphasis>property</emphasis> is a (feature,value) pair, expressed as
  &lt;feature&gt;value.</para>

  <para>A <emphasis>subfeature</emphasis> is a feature which only exists in the
  presence of its parent feature, and whose identity can be derived
  (in the context of its parent) from its value. A subfeature's
  parent can never be another subfeature. Thus, features and their
  subfeatures form a two-level hierarchy.</para>

  <para>A <emphasis>value-string</emphasis> for a feature <emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis> is a string of
  the form
  <literal>value-subvalue1-subvalue2</literal>...<literal>-subvalueN</literal>, where
  <literal>value</literal> is a legal value for <emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis> and
  <literal>subvalue1</literal>...<literal>subvalueN</literal> are legal values of some
  of <emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis>'s subfeatures. For example, the properties
  <literal>&lt;toolset&gt;gcc &lt;toolset-version&gt;3.0.1</literal> can be
  expressed more conscisely using a value-string, as
  <literal>&lt;toolset&gt;gcc-3.0.1</literal>.</para>

  <para>A <emphasis>property set</emphasis> is a set of properties (i.e. a
  collection without dublicates), for instance:
  <literal>&lt;toolset&gt;gcc &lt;runtime-link&gt;static</literal>.</para>

  <para>A <emphasis>property path</emphasis> is a property set whose elements have
  been joined into a single string separated by slashes. A property
  path representation of the previous example would be
  <literal>&lt;toolset&gt;gcc/&lt;runtime-link&gt;static</literal>.</para>

  <para>A <emphasis>build specification</emphasis> is a property set which fully
  describes the set of features used to build a target.</para>

      </section>
      <section id="bbv2.reference.features.validity">
        <title>Property Validity</title>

          <para>
            For <link linkend=
            "bbv2.reference.features.attributes.free">free</link>
            features, all values are valid. For all other features,
            the valid values are explicitly specified, and the build
            system will report an error for the use of an invalid
            feature-value. Subproperty validity may be restricted so
            that certain values are valid only in the presence of
            certain other subproperties. For example, it is possible
            to specify that the <code>&lt;gcc-target&gt;mingw</code>
            property is only valid in the presence of
            <code>&lt;gcc-version&gt;2.95.2</code>.
          </para>

      </section>
      <section id="bbv2.reference.features.attributes">
        <title>Feature Attributes</title>

  <para>Each feature has a collection of zero or more of the following
  attributes. Feature attributes are low-level descriptions of how
  the build system should interpret a feature's values when they
  appear in a build request. We also refer to the attributes of
  properties, so that a <emphasis>incidental</emphasis> property, for example, is
  one whose feature is has the <emphasis>incidental</emphasis> attribute.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis>incidental</emphasis></para>

      <para>Incidental features are assumed not to affect build
      products at all. As a consequence, the build system may use
      the same file for targets whose build specification differs
      only in incidental features. A feature which controls a
      compiler's warning level is one example of a likely
      incidental feature.</para>

      <para>Non-incidental features are assumed to affect build
      products, so the files for targets whose build specification
      differs in non-incidental features are placed in different
      directories as described in "target paths" below. [ where? ]
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <anchor id="bbv2.reference.features.attributes.propagated"/>
        <emphasis>propagated</emphasis>
      </para>

      <para>Features of this kind are
      propagated to dependencies. That is, if a <link linkend=
      "bbv2.advanced.targets.main">main target</link> is built using a
      propagated
      property, the build systems attempts to use the same property
      when building any of its dependencies as part of that main
      target. For instance, when an optimized exectuable is
      requested, one usually wants it to be linked with optimized
      libraries. Thus, the <literal>&lt;optimization&gt;</literal> feature is
      propagated.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
      <anchor id="bbv2.reference.features.attributes.free"/>
      <emphasis>free</emphasis>
      </para>

      <para>Most features have a finite set of allowed values, and can
      only take on a single value from that set in a given build
      specification. Free features, on the other hand, can have
      several values at a time and each value can be an arbitrary
      string. For example, it is possible to have several
      preprocessor symbols defined simultaneously:</para>

<programlisting>
&lt;define&gt;NDEBUG=1 &lt;define&gt;HAS_CONFIG_H=1
</programlisting>

    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis>optional</emphasis></para>

      <para>An optional feature is a feature which is not required to
      appear in a build specification. Every non-optional non-free
      feature has a default value which is used when a value for
      the feature is not otherwise specified, either in a target's
      requirements or in the user's build request. [A feature's
      default value is given by the first value listed in the
      feature's declaration. -- move this elsewhere - dwa]</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis>symmetric</emphasis></para>

      <para>A symmetric feature's default value is not automatically
      included in <link linkend=
      "bbv2.reference.variants">build variants</link>.  Normally
      a feature only generates a subvariant directory when its
      value differs from the value specified by the build variant,
      leading to an assymmetric subvariant directory structure for
      certain values of the feature. A symmetric feature, when
      relevant to the toolset, always generates a corresponding
      subvariant directory.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis>path</emphasis></para>

      <para>The value of a path feature specifies a path. The path is
      treated as relative to the directory of Jamfile where path
      feature is used and is translated appropriately by the build
      system when the build is invoked from a different
      directory</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis>implicit</emphasis></para>

      <para>Values of implicit features alone identify the feature.
      For example, a user is not required to write
      "&lt;toolset&gt;gcc", but can simply write "gcc". Implicit
      feature names also don't appear in variant paths, although
      the values do. Thus: bin/gcc/... as opposed to
      bin/toolset-gcc/.... There should typically be only a few
      such features, to avoid possible name clashes.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis>composite</emphasis></para>

      <para>Composite features actually correspond to groups of
      properties. For example, a build variant is a composite
      feature. When generating targets from a set of build
      properties, composite features are recursively expanded and
      <emphasis>added</emphasis> to the build property set, so rules can find
      them if neccessary. Non-composite non-free features override
      components of composite features in a build property set.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis>link-incompatible</emphasis></para>

      <para>See <link linkend=
      "bbv2.reference.variants.compat">below</link>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis>dependency</emphasis></para>

      <para>The value of dependency feature if a target reference.
      When used for building of a main target, the value of
      dependency feature is treated as additional dependency.</para>

      <para>For example, dependency features allow to state that
      library A depends on library B. As the result, whenever an
      application will link to A, it will also link to B.
      Specifying B as dependency of A is different from adding B to
      the sources of A. <!-- Need to clarify this. --></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Features which are neither free nor incidental are called
  <emphasis>base</emphasis> features.</para>

  <para>TODO: document active features..</para>

      </section>
      <section id="bbv2.reference.features.declaration">
        <title>Feature Declaration</title>

        <para>The low-level feature declaration interface is the
        <literal>feature</literal> rule from the
        <literal>feature</literal> module:

<programlisting>
rule feature ( name : allowed-values * : attributes * )
</programlisting>

        A feature's allowed-values may be extended wit The build
system will provide high-level rules which define features in terms
of valid and useful combinations of attributes.
        </para>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.reference.variants">
      <title>Build Variants</title>

      <para>
A build variant, or (simply variant) is a special kind of composite
  feature which automatically incorporates the default values of
  features that . Typically you'll want at least two separate
  variants: one for debugging, and one for your release code. [
  Volodya says: "Yea, we'd need to mention that it's a composite
  feature and describe how they are declared, in pacticular that
  default values of non-optional features are incorporated into
  build variant automagically. Also, do we wan't some variant
  inheritance/extension/templates. I don't remember how it works in
  V1, so can't document this for V2.". Will clean up soon -DWA ]
      </para>

      <section id="bbv2.reference.variants.compat">
        <title>Link compatible and incompatible properties</title>

  <para>When the build system tries to generate a target (such as
  library dependency) matching a given build request, it may find
  that an exact match isn't possible &#x2014; for example, the
  target may impose additonal build requirements. We need to
  determine whether a buildable version of that target can actually
  be used.</para>

  <para>The build request can originate in many ways: it may come
  directly from the user's command-line, from a dependency of a
  main target upon a library, or from a dependency of a target upon
  an executable used to build that target, for example. For each
  way, there are different rules whether we can use a given
  subvariant or not. The current rules are described below.</para>

  <para>Two property sets are called <emphasis>link-compatible</emphasis> when
  targets with those property sets can be used interchangably. In
  turn, two property sets are link compatible when there's no
  link-incompatible feature which has different values in those
  property sets.</para>

  <para>When building of a main target is requested from a command
  line or some project, link-compatibility is not considered. When
  building is requested by other main target, via sources or
  dependency properties, the requested and actual property sets
  must be link-compatible, otherwise a warning is produced.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Rationale:</emphasis>Link-compatibility is not considered when
  main target is requested by a project, because it causes problems
  in practice. For example, some parts of a project might be
  single-threaded, while others &#x2014; multi-threaded. They are
  not link-compatible, but they are not linked, either. So, there's
  no need to issue error or warning. The errors used to be
  generated, and only caused problems.</para>

      </section>
      <section id="bbv2.reference.variants.proprefine">
        <title>Definition of property refinement</title>

  <para>When a target with certain properties is requested, and that
  target requires some set of properties, it is needed to find the
  set of properties to use for building. This process is called
  <emphasis>property refinement</emphasis> and is performed by these rules</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        If original properties and required properties are not
        link-compatible, refinement fails.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Each property in the required set is added to the original
        property set
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        If the original property set includes property with a different
        value of non free feature, that property is removed.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="bbv2.reference.variants.propcond">
        <title>Conditional properties</title>

  <para>Sometime it's desirable to apply certain requirements only for
  specific combination of other properties. For example, one of
  compilers that you use issues a poinless warning that you want to
  suppress by passing a command line option to it. You would not
  want to pass that option to other compilers. Condititional
  properties allow to do that. Their systax is:</para>

<programlisting>
property ( "," property ) * ":" property
</programlisting>

    <para>
For example, the problem above would be solved by:

<programlisting>
exe hello : hello.cpp : &lt;toolset&gt;yfc:&lt;cxxflags&gt;-disable-pointless-warning ;
</programlisting>
    </para>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.reference.init">
      <title>Initialization</title>

  <para>bjam's first job upon startup is to load the Jam code which
  implements the build system. To do this, it searches for a file
  called "boost-build.jam", first in the invocation directory, then
  in its parent and so forth up to the filesystem root, and finally
  in the directories specified by the environment variable
  BOOST_BUILD_PATH. When found, the file is interpreted, and should
  specify the build system location by calling the boost-build
  rule:</para>

<programlisting>
rule boost-build ( location ? )
</programlisting>

      <para>
If location is a relative path, it is treated as relative to
the directory of boost-build.jam. The directory specified by
location and directories in BOOST_BUILD_PATH are then searched for
a file called bootstrap.jam which is interpreted and is expected to
bootstrap the build system. This arrangement allows the build
system to work without any command-line or environment variable
settings. For example, if the build system files were located in a
directory "build-system/" at your project root, you might place a
boost-build.jam at the project root containing:

<programlisting>
boost-build build-system ;
</programlisting>

In this case, running bjam anywhere in the project tree will
automatically find the build system.</para>

  <para>The default "bootstrap.jam", after loading some standard
  definitions, loads two files, which can be provided/customised by
  user: "site-config.jam" and "user-config.jam".</para>

  <para>Locations where those files a search are summarized below:</para>

  <table id="bbv2.reference.init.config">
    <title>Search paths for configuration files</title>

    <tgroup cols="3">
      <thead>

    <row>
      <entry></entry>

      <entry>site-config.jam</entry>

      <entry>user-config.jam</entry>
    </row>

      </thead>
      <tbody>

    <row>
      <entry>Linux</entry>

      <entry>
        <simpara>/etc</simpara>
        <simpara>$HOME</simpara>
        <simpara>$BOOST_BUILD_PATH</simpara>
     </entry>

      <entry>
        <simpara>$HOME</simpara>
        <simpara>$BOOST_BUILD_PATH</simpara>
      </entry>
    </row>

    <row>
      <entry>Windows</entry>

      <entry>
        <simpara>$SystemRoot</simpara>
        <simpara>$HOME</simpara>
        <simpara>$BOOST_BUILD_PATH</simpara>
      </entry>

      <entry>
        <simpara>$HOME</simpara>
        <simpara>$BOOST_BUILD_PATH</simpara>
      </entry>
    </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

   <para>
Boost.Build comes with default versions of those files,
  which can serve as templates for customized versions.
   </para>

    </section>
    <section id="bbv2.reference.commandline">
      <title>Command line</title>

  <para>The command line may contain:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><simpara>Jam options,</simpara></listitem>

    <listitem><simpara>Boost.Build <link linkend=
      "bbv2.reference.init.options">options</link>,</simpara></listitem>

    <listitem><simpara>Command line arguments</simpara></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

      <section id="bbv2.reference.init.args">
        <title>Command line arguments</title>

        <para>
        Command line arguments specify targets and build
  request using the following rules.
        </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        An argument which does not contain slashes or the "="
    symbol is either a value of an implicit feature, or target to
    be built. It is taken to be value of a feature if appropriate
    feature exists. Otherwise, it is considered a <link linkend=
    "bbv2.advanced.ids">target id</link>. Special target name "clean"
    has the same effect as "--clean" option.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        An argument with either slashes or the "=" symbol specifies
    a number of <link linkend="bbv2.reference.buildreq">build
    request</link>
    elements. In the simplest form, it's just a set of properties,
    separated by slashes, which become a single build request
    element, for example:

<programlisting>
borland/&lt;runtime-link&gt;static
</programlisting>

More complex form is used to save typing. For example,
instead of

<programlisting>
borland/runtime-link=static borland/runtime-link=dynamic
</programlisting>

one can use

<programlisting>
borland/runtime-link=static,dynamic
</programlisting>

Exactly, the conversion from argument to build request
elements is performed by (1) splitting the argument at each slash,
(2) converting each split part into a set of properties and (3)
taking all possible combination of the property sets. Each split
part should have the either the form

<programlisting>
<emphasis>feature-name</emphasis>=<emphasis>feature-value1</emphasis>[","<emphasis>feature-valueN</emphasis>]*   
</programlisting>

or, in case of implict feature

<programlisting>
<emphasis>feature-value1</emphasis>[","<emphasis>feature-valueN</emphasis>;]*   
</programlisting>

and will be converted into property set

<programlisting>
&lt;feature-name&gt;feature-value1 .... &lt;feature-name&gt;feature-valueN
</programlisting>

      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

      <para>
For example, the command line

<programlisting>
target1 debug gcc/runtime-link=dynamic,static
</programlisting>

would cause target called <literal>target1</literal> to be rebuild in
debug mode, except that for gcc, both dynamically and statically
linked binaries would be created.
      </para>

      </section>
      <section id="bbv2.reference.init.options">
        <title>Command line options</title>

  <para>All of the Boost.Build options start with the "--" prefix.
  They are described in the following table.</para>

  <table>
    <title>Command line options</title>
    <tgroup cols="2">

    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry>Option</entry>

        <entry>Description</entry>
      </row>
    </thead>

    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry><literal>--version</literal></entry>

        <entry>Prints information on Boost.Build and Boost.Jam
        versions.</entry>
      </row>

      <row id="bbv2.reference.init.options.help">
        <entry><literal>--help</literal></entry>

        <entry>Access to the online help system. This prints general
        information on how to use the help system with additional
        --help* options.</entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry><literal>--clean</literal></entry>

        <entry>Removes everything instead of building. Unlike
        <literal>clean</literal> target in make, it is possible to clean only
        some targets.</entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry><literal>--debug</literal></entry>

        <entry>Enables internal checks.</entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry><literal>--dump-projects</literal></entry>

        <entry>Cause the project structure to be output.</entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry><literal>--no-error-backtrace</literal></entry>

        <entry>Don't print backtrace on errors. Primary usefull for
        testing.</entry>
      </row>

      <row>
        <entry><literal>--ignore-config</literal></entry>

        <entry>Do not load <literal>site-config.jam</literal> and
        <literal>user-config.jam</literal></entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.reference.buildreq">
      <title>Build request</title>

      <para/>
    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.reference.buildprocess">
      <title>Build process</title>

  <para>Construction of each main target begins with finding
  properties for <emphasis>this</emphasis> main target. They are found by
  processing both build request, and <emphasis>target requirements</emphasis>,
  which give properties needed for the target to build. For
  example, a given main target might require certian defines, or
  will not work unless compiled in multithreaded mode. The process
  of finding properties for main target is described in <link linkend=
  "bbv2.reference.variants.proprefine">property refinement</link>.</para>

  <para>After that, dependencies (i.e. other main targets) are build
  recursively. Build request for dependencies is not always equal
  to those of dependent &#x2014; certain properties are dropped and
  user can explicitly specify desired properties for dependencies.
  See <link linkend="bbv2.reference.features.attributes.propagated">
  propagated features</link> and <xref linkend=
  "bbv2.advanced.targets.references"/> for details.</para>

  <para>When dependencies are constructed, the dependency graph for
  this main target and for this property set is created, which
  describes which files need to be created, on which other files
  they depend and what actions are needed to construct those files.
  There's more that one method, and user can define new ones, but
  usually, this involves <emphasis>generators</emphasis> and <emphasis>target
  types</emphasis>.</para>

  <para>Target type is just a way to classify targets. For example,
  there are builtin types <literal>EXE</literal>, <literal>OBJ</literal> and
  <literal>CPP</literal>. <link linkend=
  "bbv2.reference.generators">Generators</link> are objects
  that know how to convert between different target type. When a
  target of a given type must be created, all generators for that
  type, which can handle needed properties, are found. Each is
  passed the list of sources, and either fails, or returns a
  dependency graph. If a generator cannot produce desired type from
  given sources, it may try to recursively construct types that it
  can handle from the types is was passed. This allows to try all
  possible transformations. When all generators are tried, a
  dependency graph is selected.</para>

  <para>Finally, the dependency graph is passed to underlying
  Boost.Jam program, which runs all actions needed to bring all
  main targets up-to date. At this step, implicit dependencies are
  also scanned and accounted for, as described "here." [ link? ]</para>

  <para>Given a list of targets ids and a build request, building goes
  this way. First, for each id we obtain the abstract targets
  corresponding to it. This also loads all necessary projects. If
  no target id is given, project in the current directory is used.
  Build request is expanded, and for each resulting property set,
  the <literal>generate</literal> method of all targets is called, which
  yields a list of virtual targets. After that all virtual targets
  are actualized, and target "all" is set to depend on all created
  actual targets. Lastly, depending on whether <literal>--clean</literal>
  option was given, either target "all" or target "clean" is
  updated. Generation of virtual target from abstract one is
  performed as follows:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>For project targets, all of main targets are generated
      with the same properties. Then all projects referred via
      "build-project" are generated as well. If it's not possible
      to refine requested properties with project requirements, the
      project is skipped.</para>

      <para id="bbv2.reference.buildprocess.explict">
      It is possible to disable building of certain target using the
      <literal>explicit</literal> rule, available in all project
      modules. The syntax is

<programlisting>
rule explicit ( target-name )
</programlisting>

      If this rule is invoked on a target, it will be built only
when it's explicitly requested on the command line.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        For main target, with several alternatives, one of them is
    selected as described <link linkend=
      "bbv2.reference.buildprocess.alternatives">below</link>.
    If there's only one
    alternative, it's used unconditionally.

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            All main target alternatives which requirements are
            satisfied by the build request are enumerated.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            If there are several such alternatives, the one which
            longer requirements list is selected.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        For the selected alternative

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            Each target reference in the source list are
        recursively constructed.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            Properties are refined with alternative's requirements,
        and active features in the resulting set are executed.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            Conditional properties are evaluated.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            The dependency graph for the target is constructed in a
        way which depends on the kind of main target, typically
        using generators.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        If, when building sources, the properties on recursively
    created targets are not link-compatibile with build properties,
    a warning is issued.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="bbv2.reference.buildprocess.alternatives">
        <title>Alternative selection</title>

  <para>When there are several alternatives, one of them must be
  selected. The process is as follows:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        For each alternative <emphasis>condition</emphasis> is defined
        as the set of base properies in requirements. [Note: it might be
    better to explicitly specify the condition explicitly, as in
    conditional requirements].
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        An alternative is viable only if all properties in condition
        are present in build request.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        If there's one viable alternative, it's choosen. Otherwise,
    an attempt is made to find one best alternative. An alternative
    a is better than another alternative b, iff set of properties
    in b's condition is stict subset of the set of properities of
    'a's condition. If there's one viable alternative, which is
    better than all other, it's selected. Otherwise, an error is
    reported.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.reference.headers">
      <title>Generated headers</title>

  <para>Usually, Boost.Build handles implicit dependendies completely
  automatically. For example, for C++ files, all <literal>#include</literal>
  statements are found and handled. The only aspect where user help
  might be needed is implicit dependency on generated files.</para>

  <para>By default, Boost.Build handles such dependencies within one
  main target. For example, assume that main target "app" has two
  sources, "app.cpp" and "parser.y". The latter source is converted
  into "parser.c" and "parser.h". Then, if "app.cpp" includes
  "parser.h", Boost.Build will detect this dependency. Moreover,
  since "parser.h" will be generated into a build directory, the
  path to that directory will automatically added to include
  path.</para>

  <para>Making this mechanism work across main target boundaries is
  possible, but imposes certain overhead. For that reason, if
  there's implicit dependency on files from other main targets, the
  <literal>&lt;implicit-dependency&gt;</literal> [ link ] feature must
  be used, for example:</para>

<programlisting>
lib parser : parser.y ;
exe app : app.cpp : &lt;implicit-dependency&gt;parser ;
</programlisting>

      <para>
The above example tells the build system that when scanning
all sources of "app" for implicit-dependencies, it should consider
targets from "parser" as potential dependencies.
      </para>

    </section>
    <section id="bbv2.reference.generators">
      <title>Generators</title>

  <para>To construct a main target with given properties from sources,
  it is required to create a dependency graph for that main target,
  which will also include actions to be run. The algorithm for
  creating the dependency graph is described here.</para>

  <para>The fundamental concept is <emphasis>generator</emphasis>. If encapsulates
  the notion of build tool and is capable to converting a set of
  input targets into a set of output targets, with some properties.
  Generator matches a build tool as closely as possible: it works
  only when the tool can work with requested properties (for
  example, msvc compiler can't work when requested toolset is gcc),
  and should produce exactly the same targets as the tool (for
  example, if Borland's linker produces additional files with debug
  information, generator should also).</para>

  <para>Given a set of generators, the fundamental operation is to
  construct a target of a given type, with given properties, from a
  set of targets. That operation is performed by rule
  <literal>generators.construct</literal> and the used algorithm is described
  below.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Selecting and ranking viable generators</title>

  <para>Each generator, in addition to target types that it can
  produce, have attribute that affects its applicability in
  particular sitiation. Those attributes are:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Required properties, which are properties absolutely
    necessary for the generator to work. For example, generator
    encapsulating the gcc compiler would have &lt;toolset&gt;gcc as
    required property.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Optional properties, which increase the generators
    suitability for a particual build.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  
  <para>
  Generator's required and optional properties may not include
  either free or incidental properties. (Allowing this would
  greatly complicate caching targets).
  </para>

  <para>When trying to construct a target, the first step is to select
  all possible generators for the requested target type, which
  required properties are a subset of requested properties.
  Generators which were already selected up the call stack are
  excluded. In addition, if any composing generators were selected
  up the call stack, all other composing generators are ignored
  (TODO: define composing generators). The found generators
  assigned a rank, which is the number of optional properties
  present in requested properties. Finally, generators with highest
  rank are selected for futher processing.</para>

      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Running generators</title>

  <para>When generators are selected, each is run to produce a list of
  created targets. This list might include targets which are not of
  requested types, because generators create the same targets as
  some tool, and tool's behaviour is fixed. (Note: should specify
  that in some cases we actually want extra targets). If generator
  fails, it returns an empty list. Generator is free to call
  'construct' again, to convert sources to the types it can handle.
  It also can pass modified properties to 'constuct'. However, a
  generator is not allowed to modify any propagated properties,
  otherwise when actually consuming properties we might discover
  that the set of propagated properties is different from what was
  used for building sources.</para>

  <para>For all targets which are not of requested types, we try to
  convert them to requested type, using a second call to
  <literal>construct</literal>. This is done in order to support
  transformation sequences where single source file expands to
  several later. See <ulink url=
  "http://groups.yahoo.com/group/jamboost/message/1667">this
  message</ulink> for details.</para>

      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Selecting dependency graph</title>

        <para>
  After all generators are run,
  it is necessary to decide which of successfull invocation will be
  taken as final result. At the moment, this is not done. Instead,
  it is checked whether all successfull generator invocation
  returned the same target list. Error is issued otherwise.
        </para>

      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Property adjustment</title>

  <para>Because target location is determined by the build system, it
  is sometimes necessary to adjust properties, in order to not
  break actions. For example, if there's an action which generates
  a header, say "a_parser.h", and a source file "a.cpp" which
  includes that file, we must make everything work as if a_parser.h
  is generated in the same directory where it would be generated
  without any subvariants.</para>

  <para>Correct property adjustment can be done only after all targets
  are created, so the approach taken is:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        When dependency graph is constructed, each action can be
    assigned a rule for property adjustment.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        When virtual target is actualized, that rule is run and
    return the final set of properties. At this stage it can use
    information of all created virtual targets.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>In case of quoted includes, no adjustment can give 100%
  correct results. If target dirs are not changed by build system,
  quoted includes are searched in "." and then in include path,
  while angle includes are searched only in include path. When
  target dirs are changed, we'd want to make quoted includes to be
  search in "." then in additional dirs and then in the include
  path and make angle includes be searched in include path,
  probably with additional paths added at some position. Unless,
  include path already has "." as the first element, this is not
  possible. So, either generated headers should not be included
  with quotes, or first element of include path should be ".",
  which essentially erases the difference between quoted and angle
  includes. <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> there only way to get "." as include path
  into compiler command line is via verbatim compiler option. In
  all other case, Boost.Build will convert "." into directory where
  it occurs.</para>

      </section>

      <section>
      <title>Transformations cache</title>

      <para>
  Under certain conditions, an
  attempt is made to cache results of transformation search. First,
  the sources are replaced with targets with special name and the
  found target list is stored. Later, when properties, requested
  type, and source type are the same, the store target list is
  retrieved and cloned, with appropriate change in names.
      </para>

      </section>
    </section>

  </chapter>

