<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Boost//DTD BoostBook XML V1.0//EN"
  "http://www.boost.org/tools/boostbook/dtd/boostbook.dtd">

<chapter id="bbv2.tutorial">
  <title>Tutorial</title>

  <section id="bbv2.tutorial.hello">
    <title>Hello, world</title>

    <para>The simplest project that Boost.Build can construct is
    stored in example/hello directory. The targets are declared in
    a file called <filename>Jamfile</filename>, which contains the
    following:

<programlisting>
exe hello : hello.cpp ;
</programlisting>

      Even with this simple setup, you can do some interesting
      things. First of all, running "bjam" would build binary "hello"
      from hello.cpp, in debug version. After that, you can run

<screen>
bjam release
</screen>

      which would create release version of the 'hello' binary.
      Note that debug and release version would be created in different
      directories, so if you want to switch from debug to release
      version and back, no recompilation is needed. Let's extend the
      example by adding another line to Jamfile:

<programlisting>
exe hello2 : hello.cpp ;
</programlisting>

      You can now rebuild both debug and release versions:

<screen>
bjam debug release
</screen>

      You'll see that two versions of "hello2" binary are linked.
      Of course, hello.cpp won't be recompiled. Now you decide to remove
      all build products. You do that with the following command

<screen>
bjam --clean debug release
</screen>

      It's also possible to create or clean only specific targets.
      Both following commands are legal and create or clean only files
      that belonging the the named binary:

<screen>
bjam hello2
bjam --clean hello2
</screen>
      </para>

    </section>
    <section id="bbv2.tutorial.properties">
      <title>Properties</title>

  <para>Boost.Build attempts to allow building different variants of
  projects, e.g. for debugging and release, or in single and
  multithreaded mode. In order to stay portable, it uses the
  concept of <emphasis>features</emphasis>, which is abstract aspect of
  build configuration. <emphasis>Property</emphasis> is just a (feature,
  value) pair. For example, there's a feature "debug-symbols", which can
  have a value of "on" or "off". When users asks to build project is a
  particual value, Boost.Build will automatically find the
  appropriate flags to the used compiler.</para>

  <para>The "release" and "debug" in bjam invocation that we've seen
  are just are short form of specifying values of feature
  "variant". There is a lot of builtin features, and it's possible
  to write something like:</para>

<screen>
bjam release inlining=off debug-symbols=on
</screen>

      <para>
      The first command line element specified the value of feature
      "variant". The feature is very common and is therefore special
      &#x2014; it's possible to specify only value. Another feature,
      "inlining" is not special, and you should use

<screen>
feature-name=feature-value
</screen>

      syntax for it. Complete description of features can be found
      <link linkend="bbv2.reference.features">here</link>. The set of
      properties specified in the command line constitute
      <emphasis>build request</emphasis> &#x2014; the desired properties
      for requested targets, or for the project in the current
      directory. The actual set of properties used for building is
      often different. For example, when compiling a program you need
      some include paths. It's not reasonable to ask the user to specify
      those paths with each bjam invocation, so must be specified in
      Jamfile and added to the build request. For another example,
      certain application can only be linked in multithreaded mode. To
      support such situations, every target is allowed to specify
      <emphasis>requirements</emphasis> -- properties that are required
      to its building. Consider this example:

<programlisting>
exe hello 
    : hello.cpp
    : &lt;include&gt;/home/ghost/Work/boost &lt;threading&gt;multi
</programlisting>

    In this case, when hello is build, the two specified properties will
    always be present. This leads to a question: what if user explictly
    requested single-threading. The answer is that requirement can
    affect build properties only to a certain degree: the requested and
    actual properties must be link-compatible. See <xref linkend=
    "bbv2.reference.variants.compat"/> below. If they are not link
    compatible, the bulding of the target is skipped. Previously, we've
    added "hello2" target. Seems like we have to specify the same
    requirements for it, which results in duplication. But there's a
    better way. Each project (i.e. each Jamfile), can specify a set of
    attributes, including requirements:

<programlisting>
project 
    : requirements &lt;include&gt;/home/ghost/Work/boost &lt;threading&gt;multi 
    ;

exe hello : hello.cpp ;
exe hello2 : hello.cpp ;
</programlisting>

      The effect would be as if we specified this requirement for
      both "hello" and "hello2".
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.tutorial.hierarchy">
      <title>Project hierarchy</title>

  <para>So far we only considered examples with one project (i.e. with
  one Jamfile). Typically, you'd have a lot of projects organized
  into a tree. At the top of the tree there's <emphasis>project
  root</emphasis>. This is a directory which contains, besides Jamfile, a
  file called "project-root.jam". Each other Jamfile has a single
  parent, which is the Jamfile in the nearest parent directory. For
  example, in the following directory layout:</para>

<screen>
[top] 
  |
  |-- Jamfile
  |-- project-root.jam
  |
  |-- src
  |    |
  |    |-- Jamfile
  |    \-- app.cpp
  | 
  \-- lib
       |
       |-- lib1
       |    |
       |    |-- Jamfile
            |-- lib1.cpp
</screen>

      <para>
project root is at top. Both src/Jamfile and lib/lib1/Jamfile
have [top]/Jamfile as parent project. Projects inherit all
attributes (such as requirements) from their parents. When the same
attributes are specified in the project, they are combined with
inherited ones. For example, if [top]/Jamfile has

<programlisting>
&lt;include&gt;/home/ghost/local
</programlisting>

in requirements, then all other projects will have that in
their requirements too. Of course, any project can add additional
includes. More details can be found in the section on <link linkend=
"bbv2.advanced.projects">projects</link>. Projects are not automatically
built when
their parents are built. You should specify this explicitly. In our
example, [top]/Jamfile might contain:

<programlisting>
build-project src ;
</programlisting>

      It will cause project in src to be built whenever project in
[top] is built. However, targets in lib/lib1 will be built only if
required. For example, there may be 10 targets, and two of them are
used by targets in src/Jamfile. Then, only those two targets will
be built.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.tutorial.libs">
      <title>Using libraries</title>

      <para>Let's continue the above example and see how src/Jamfile
      can use libraries from
  lib/lib1. (TODO: need to make this section consistent with
  "examples-v2/libraries". Assume lib/lib1/Jamfile contains:

<programlisting>
lib lib1 : lib1.cpp ;
</programlisting>

      Then, to use this library in src/Jamfile, we can write:

<programlisting>
exe app : app.cpp ../lib/lib1//lib1 ;
</programlisting>

While "app.cpp" is a regular source file, "../lib/lib1//lib1"
is a reference to another target, here, library "lib1" declared in
Jamfile at "../lib/lib1". When linking the "app" binary, the needed
version of the library will be built and linked in. But what is
meant by "needed"? For example, we can request to build "app" with
properties

<programlisting>
&lt;optimization&gt;full &lt;cxxflags&gt;-w-8080
</programlisting>

Which properties must be used for "lib1"? The answer is that
some properties are <emphasis>propagated</emphasis> &#x2014; Boost.Build attemps
to use dependencies with the same value of propagated features. The
&lt;optimization&gt; feature is propagated, so both "app" and
"lib1" will be compiled with full optimization. But
&lt;cxxflags&gt; feature is not propagated: its value will be added
as-is to compiler flags for "a.cpp", but won't affect "lib1". There
is still a couple of problems. First, the library probably has some
headers which must be used when compiling "app.cpp". We could use
requirements on "app" to add those includes, but then this work
will be repeated for all programs which use "lib1". A better
solution is to modify lib/lib1/Jamfilie in this way:

<programlisting>
project 
    : usage-requirements &lt;include&gt;.
    ;

lib lib1 : lib1.cpp ;
</programlisting>

Usage requirements are requirements which are applied to
dependents. In this case, &lt;include&gt; will be applied to all
targets which use "lib1" &#x2014; i.e. targets which have "lib1"
either in sources or in dependency properties. You'd need to
specify usage requirements only once, and programs which use "lib1"
don't have to care about include paths any longer. Or course, the
path will be interpreted relatively to "lib/lib1" and will be
adjusted according to the <command>bjam</command>s invocation
directory. For
example, if building from project root, the final compiler's
command line will contain <option>-Ilib/lib1</option>.
      </para>

  <para>The second problem is that we hardcode the path to library's
  Jamfile. Imagine it's hardcoded in 20 different places and we
  change the directory layout. The solution is to use project ids
  &#x2014; symbolic names, not tied to directory layout. First, we
  assign a project id to Jamfile in lib/lib1:</para>

<programlisting>
project lib1
    : usage-requirements &lt;include&gt;.
    ;
</programlisting>

      <para>
Second, we use the project id to refer to the library in
src/Jamfile:

<programlisting>
exe app : app.cpp /lib1//lib1 ;
</programlisting>

The "/lib1//lib1" syntax is used to refer to target "lib1" in
project with global id "/lib1" (the slash is used to specify global
id). This way, users of "lib1" do not depend on its location, only
on id, which is supposedly stable. The only thing left, it to make
sure that src/Jamfile knows the project id that it uses. We add to
[top]/Jamfile the following line:

<programlisting>
use-project /lib1 : lib/lib1 ;
</programlisting>

Now, all projects can refer to "lib1" using the symbolic
name. If the library is moved somewhere, only a single line in the
top-level Jamfile should be changed.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.tutorial.depends">
      <title>Library dependencies</title>

  <para>The previous example was simple. Often, there are long chains
  of dependencies between libraries. The main application is a thin
  wrapper on top of library with core logic, which uses library of
  utility functions, which uses boost filesystem library.
  Expressing these dependencies is straightforward:</para>

<programlisting>
lib utils : utils.cpp /boost/filesystem//fs ;   
lib core : core.cpp utils ;
exe app : app.cpp core ;
</programlisting>

  <para>So, what's the reason to even mention this case? First,
  because it's a bit more complex that it seems. When using shared
  linking, libraries are build just as written, and everything will
  work. However, what happens with static linking? It's not
  possible to include another library in static library.
  Boost.Build solves this problem by returning back library targets
  which appear as sources for static libraries. In this case, if
  everything is built statically, the "app" target will link not
  only "core" library, but also "utils" and
  "/boost/filesystem//fs".</para>

  <para>So, the net result is that the above code will work for both
  static linking and for shared linking.</para>

  <para>Sometimes, you want all applications in some project to link
  to a certain library. Putting the library in sources of all
  targets is possible, but verbose. You can do better by using
  &lt;library&gt; property. For example, if "/boost/filesystem//fs"
  should be linked to all applications in your project, you can add
  &lt;library&gt;/boost/filesystem//fs to requirements of the
  project, like this:</para>

<programlisting>
project 
   : requirements &lt;library&gt;/boost/filesystem//fs
   ;   
</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.tutorial.linkage">
      <title>Static and shared libaries</title>

      <para>While the
  previous section explained how to create and use libraries, it
  omitted one important detail. Libraries can be either
  <emphasis>static</emphasis>, which means they are included in executable
  files which use them, or <emphasis>shared</emphasis> (a.k.a.
  <emphasis>dynamic</emphasis>), which are only referred to from executables,
  and must be available at run time. Boost.Build can work with both
  types. By default, all libraries are shared. This is much more
  efficient in build time and space. But the need to install all
  libraries to some location is not always convenient, especially
  for debug builds. Also, if the installed shared library changes,
  all application which use it might start to behave differently.
      </para>

  <para>Static libraries do not suffer from these problems, but
  considerably increase the size of application. Before describing
  static libraries, it's reasonable to give another, quite simple
  approach. If your project is built with
  &lt;hardcode-dll-paths&gt;true property, then the application
  will include the full paths for all shared libraries, eliminating
  the above problems. Unfortunately, you no longer can move shared
  library to a different location, which makes this option suitable
  only for debug builds. Further, only gcc compiler supports this
  option.</para>

  <para>Building a library statically is easy. You'd need to change
  the value of &lt;link&gt; feature from it's deafault value
  <literal>shared</literal>, to <literal>static</literal>. So, to build everything as
  static libraries, you'd say</para>

<screen>
bjam link=static
</screen>

      <para>
on the command line. The linking mode can be fine-tuned on
per-target basis.

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            Suppose your library can be only build statically. This is
            easily achieved using requirements:

<programlisting>
lib l : l.cpp : &lt;link&gt;static ;
</programlisting>
 
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            What if library can be both static and shared, but when
            using it in specific executable, you want it static?
            <link linkend="bbv2.advanced.targets.references">Target
            references</link> are here to help:

<programlisting>
exe important : main.cpp helpers/&lt;link&gt;static ;
</programlisting>

            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
    What if the library is defined in some other project, which
    you cannot change. But still, you want static linking to that
    library in all cases. You can use target references everywhere:

<programlisting>
exe e1 : e1.cpp /other_project//lib1/&lt;link&gt;static ;
exe e10 : e10.cpp /other_project//lib1/&lt;link&gt;static ;
</programlisting>

but that's far from being convenient. Another way is to
introduce a level of indirection: create a local target, which will
refer to static version of <filename>lib1</filename>. Here's the
solution:

<programlisting>
alias lib1 : /other_project//lib1/&lt;link&gt;static ;
exe e1 : e1.cpp lib1 ;
exe e10 : e10.cpp lib1 ;
</programlisting>

(Note, that the "alias" target type is not yet implemented,
but it's quite simple to do. I bet it's waiting for you to do it
;-))
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="bbv2.tutorial.prebuilt">
      <title>Prebuilt targets</title>

      <para>
      We've just learned how to use libraries which are created by
      Boost.Build. But some libraries are not. At the same time, those
      libraries can have different versions (release and debug, for
      example), that we
  should select depending on build properties. Prebuilt targets
  provide a mechanism for that. Jamfile in lib/lib2 can contain:

<programlisting>
lib lib2
    : 
    : &lt;file&gt;lib2_release.a &lt;variant&gt;release
    ;

lib lib2
    : 
    : &lt;file&gt;lib2_debug.a &lt;variant&gt;debug
    ;
</programlisting>

This defines two alternatives for target "lib2", and for each
one names a prebuilt file. Naturally, there are no sources.
Instead, the &lt;file&gt; feature is used to specify the file name.
Which alternative is selected depends on properties of dependents.
If "app" binary should use "lib2", we can write:

<programlisting>
exe app : app.cpp /lib/lib1//lib2 ../lib/lib2//lib2 ;
</programlisting>

If we build release version of "app", then it will be linked
with "lib2_release.a", and debug version will use "lib2_debug.a".
Another important kind of prebuilt targets are system libraries
&#x2014; more specifically, libraries which are automatically found
by the compiler. E.g. gcc uses "-l" switch for that. Such libraries
should be declared almost like regular ones:

<programlisting>
lib zlib : : &lt;name&gt;z ;
</programlisting>

We again don't specify any sources, but give a name which
should be passed to the compiler. In this example, and for gcc
compiler, the "-lz" option will be added. Paths where library
should be searched can also be specified:

<programlisting>
lib zlib : : &lt;name&gt;z &lt;search&gt;/opt/lib ;
</programlisting>

And, of course, two variants can be used:

<programlisting>
lib zlib : : &lt;name&gt;z &lt;variant&gt;release ;
lib zlib : : &lt;name&gt;z_d &lt;variant&gt;debug ;
</programlisting>

Of course, you'll probably never in your life need debug
version of zlib, but for other libraries this is quite reasonable.
      </para>

  <para>More advanced use of prebuilt target is descibed in <ulink
  url="doc/recipes.html#site_config_targets">recipes</ulink>.</para>

    </section>

</chapter>

