<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE library PUBLIC "-//Boost//DTD BoostBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.boost.org/tools/boostbook/dtd/boostbook.dtd">
<section id="string_algo.intro" last-revision="$Date: 2004/03/04 22:12:09 $">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
        The String Algorithm Library provides a generic implementation of
        string-related algorithms which are missing in STL. It is an extension
        to the algorithms library of STL and it includes trimming, case conversion, 
        predicates and find/replace functions. All of them come in different variants 
        so it is easier to choose the best fit for a particular need.
    </para>
    <para>
        The implementation is not restricted to work with a particular container 
        (like a <code>std::basic_string</code>), rather it is as generic as
        possible. This generalization is not compromising the performance since
        algorithms are using container specific features when it means a performance
        gain.
    </para>
    <para>      
        The library has layered structure to simplify the usage without sacrificing the
        generalization. 

        The easy-to-use interface, defined in the namespace <code>boost</code>, represents the first layer. 
        Algorithms and classes defined here do not offer a lot of customization opportunities 
        rather they are provided in more different variants, so a user can chose the 
        one that suits her needs.

        The second layer, defined in the namespace <code>boost::string_algo</code>, on the 
        other hand, is generic. Basically it contains the same set of algorithms as the first layer,
        but the interface is more flexible and allows more customization, but it is harder to use.
        The first layer is implemented as set of wrappers around the second layer.
    </para>
    <para>
        The documentation is divided into several sections. For a quick start read the 
        <link linkend="string_algo.usage">Usage</link> section. 
        <link linkend="string_algo.design">The Design Topics</link>,
        <link linkend="string_algo.concept">Concepts</link> and <link linkend="string_algo.rationale">Rationale</link>
        provide some explanation about the library design and structure an explain how it should be used.
        See the <link linkend="string_algo.reference">Reference</link> for the complete list of provided utilities
        and algorithms. Functions and classes in the reference are organized by the headers in which they are defined.
        The reference contains links to the detailed description for every entity in the library.
    </para>
</section>
