<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE library PUBLIC "-//Boost//DTD BoostBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.boost.org/tools/boostbook/dtd/boostbook.dtd">
<section id="string_algo.rationale" last-revision="$Date: 2004/03/04 22:12:09 $">
    <title>Rationale</title>

    <using-namespace name="boost"/>
    <using-namespace name="boost::string_algo"/>
    
    <section id="string_algo.structure">
        <title>Library structure</title>

        <para>
            When designing a library it is always a problem to find a balance between generalization
            and usability. A generic utility can have a wider range of usage with more options for extensibility,
            but it can also bring unwanted complexity for everyday usage. 
        </para>
        <para>
            Imagine a library for drawing geometric objects. It can contain one generic function <code>draw()</code>
            with many parameters specifying what to draw, like size, number of edges, shape etc.
            This would allow you to draw almost anything, but usually a user only needs to draw 
            only a triangle or a square and she will have to specify this simple request in a 
            very complicated way.For this purpose two functions, <code>draw_triangle()</code> and
            <code>draw_square()</code>, would suit much better then a generic <code>draw()</code> function.
        </para>
        <para>
            The String Algorithm Library solves this problem by dividing the interface into two layers.
            The first layer (defined in the namespace boost) contains ready to use algorithms specialized
            for common tasks. They are provided in multiple variants to better suit specific needs.
            The second layer (defined in the namespace <code>boost::string_algo</code>), provides generic interfaces with
            more options for extending and tunning. 
        <para>
        </para>
            For instance, a <functionname>boost::trim()</functionname> algorithm trims spaces from 
            an input string. When there is a need to trim something else, there is 
            <functionname>boost::string_algo::trim()</functionname> which interface allows one to specify a 
            predicate which selects the characters to be removed.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section it="string_algo.locale">
        <title>Locales</title>

        <para>
            Locales have a very close relation to string processing. They contain information about
            the character sets and are used, for example, to change the case of characters and 
            to classify the characters. 
        </para>
        <para>
            C++ allows to work with multiple different instances of locales at once. If an algorithm
            manipulates some data in a way that requires the usage of locales, there must be a way
            to specify them. However, one instance of locales is sufficient for most of the applications,
            and for a user it could be very tedious to specify which locales to use on every place 
            where it is needed. 
        </para> 
        <para>
            Fortunately, the C++ standard allows to specify the <emphasis>global</emphasis> locales (using static member
            function <code>std:locale::global()</code>). When instantiating an
            <code>std::locale</code> class without explicit information, the instance will 
            be initialized with the <emphasis>global</emphasis> locale. It means, that if an algorithm needs a locale,
            it should have an <code>std::locale</code> parameter with default value <code>std::locale()</code>.
            If a user needs to specify locales explicitly, she can do so. Otherwise the <emphasis>global</emphasis>
            locales are used.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="string_algo.regex">
        <title>Regular Expressions</title>

        <para>
            Regular expressions are an essential part of text processing. For this reason, the library 
            provides also regex variants of some algorithms. The library does not try to replace
            <libraryname>Boost.Regex</libraryname>, but it merely wraps its functionality in a new interface.
            As a part of this library regex algorithms integrate smoothly with other components which 
            brings additional value.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
